<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

    <title>Blades</title>
    <link rel="related" href="" />
    <id></id>
    
    <author>
        <name>Maros Grego</name>
        
        
    </author>
    
    <subtitle></subtitle>
    <generator>blades</generator>
    <updated>2020-10-13T17:06:02Z</updated>


    <entry>
        <title>Index</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="/" />
        <id></id>
        <summary></summary>
        <content><code class="highlighted">
<p><strong>bla</strong>zing fast
<strong>de</strong>ad simple
<strong>s</strong>tatic site generator</p>
</code>
<p>Blades is made to do one job and do it well - generate HTML files from the provided
content using the provided templates.<br />
Thanks to the amazing <a href="https://github.com/maciejhirsz/ramhorns">Ramhorns</a> templating engine,
<a href="https://serde.rs/lifetimes.html#borrowing-data-in-a-derived-impl">zero-copy</a> deserialisation
and <a href="https://github.com/rayon-rs/rayon">rayon</a> parallel iterators, it renders the whole site in
milliseconds, possibly up to <a href="https://github.com/grego/ssg-bench">10 times</a> faster than other generators like Hugo.</p>
<p>It's made for easy setup and use. A static site generator should be a no brainer.
It uses <a href="https://mustache.github.io/mustache.5.html">mustache</a> templates with extremely minimal
and obvious syntax (really, like 7 rules!), while providing the necessary building blocks
to let you focus on your content.</p>
<p>You may categorise your pages into taxonomies (like categories or tags), use the usual features
like pagination or breadcrumbs and even generate image galleries.<br />
Sitemap and RSS feed are automatically rendered.<br />
All done without hassle, faster than you blink.</p>
<h2>Why not <em><code>blades</code></em>?</h2>
<p>Unlike other monolithic generators, Blades is modest in its scope. All it does is generating your site.
It doesn't do any fancy stuff like transpiling Haskell to minified Javascript, or ever
watching the site for changes. For that, you can use a dedicated tool like
<a href="https://github.com/grego/caretaker">caretaker</a>.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, if you have a feature request or ran into some issue using Blades, please submit an
<a href="https://github.com/grego/blades">issue</a>. It is a hobby project, so any contribution
is welcome! <code>:)</code></p>
<h2>Why <em><code>blades</code></em>?</h2>
<p>They shave the <a href="https://mustache.github.io/mustache.5.html">mustache</a> off.</p>
</content>
        <updated>2020-10-01T14:41:12Z</updated>
    </entry>
    

    <entry>
        <title>Getting started</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="/getting_started.html" />
        <id>/getting_started</id>
        <summary></summary>
        <content><p>Currently, Blades is available on <a href="https://aur.archlinux.org/packages/blades-bin/">AUR</a>. You can
install it with some AUR helper, like<br />
<code>yay -S blades-bin</code>.</p>
<p>If you have the Rust toolchain installed, you can install Blades from <a href="https://crates.io/crates/blades">Crates.io</a></p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">cargo install blades
</code></pre>
<p>If you would like to have it included in your favourite package repository, <a href="https://github.com/grego/blades">submit an issue</a>.</p>
<p>Then, you can run the executable <code>blades</code> with the following subcommands:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>init</code>: Initialise the site in the current directory, creating the basic files and folders</li>
<li><code>build</code>: Build the site according to config, content, templates and themes in the current directory</li>
<li><code>colocate</code>: Move the assets from the &quot;assets&quot; directory and from the theme, if one is used, into the output directory</li>
<li><code>all</code>: Build the site and colocate the assets</li>
<li><code>lazy</code>: Build the site and (colocate assets only if the theme was switched) [default]</li>
<li><code>new</code>: Create a new page</li>
</ul>
<h2>Themes</h2>
<p>When you specify a theme in the <a href="config.html">config</a>, templates and assets from the theme are used.
Every site that doesn't use a theme can be used as a theme for another site.
Therefore, the easiest way to use a theme is to just clone the corresponding theme's repository
into the <code>themes</code> directory. A list of available themes can be found <a href="/themes">here</a>.</p>
<p>To overwrite the theme, simply use the files in the <code>templates</code>, resp. <code>assets</code> subdirectories of the
page root directory.</p>
<h2>Assets</h2>
<p>All the files from the <code>assets</code> directory (and from the theme) are moved into the directory
specified in the <a href="config.html">config</a>, which is emptied before. This is a subdirectory of the
output directory (defaults to <code>assets</code>).</p>
<p>Blades takes of the pages it rendered before and if some of them is deleted, the corresponding
files in the output directory will be deleted, too. The other files in the output directory
are left intact. This way, you can place anything in the output directory and (as long as its name
differs from all the page names and it's not in the assets subdirectory), Blades won't touch it.</p>
<h2>Meta</h2>
<p>Blades renders <a href="https://www.sitemaps.org">sitemap</a> (into <code>sitemap.xml</code>), <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atom_(Web_standard)">Atom</a> (into <code>atom.xml</code>)
and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RSS">RSS</a> (into <code>rss.xml</code>) feeds, unless explicitly disabled in the <a href="config.html">config</a>.</p>
<h2>Contribution</h2>
<p>If you found a bug or would like to see some feature in Blades, you are the most welcome to submit an issue
or a pull request! Likewise if you found something in this documentation not clear or imprecise.</p>
</content>
        <updated>2020-10-13T11:34:04Z</updated>
    </entry>
    

    <entry>
        <title>Configuration</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="/config.html" />
        <id>/config</id>
        <summary></summary>
        <content><p>The site can be configured in the file <code>Blades.toml</code> in its root directory. There, the following
variables can be set (all optional, default values shown):</p>
<code class="highlighted">
<p><em># Title of the site</em>
<strong>title</strong> = &quot;&quot;
<em># URL which the site is expected to be accessed through</em>
<strong>url</strong> = &quot;&quot;
<em># Name of the folder where theme templates and assets shall be loaded from,</em>
<em># located in the themes directory (see below)</em>
<strong>theme</strong> = &quot;&quot;
<strong>description</strong> = &quot;&quot; 
<strong>keywords</strong> = &quot;&quot;
<strong>image</strong> = &quot;&quot;</p>
<p><em># Generate sitemap</em>
<strong>sitemap</strong> = true
<em># Generate RSS feed</em>
<strong>rss</strong> = true
<em># Generate Atom feed</em>
<strong>atom</strong> = true
<em># Generate taxonomies that were not explicitly defined in this config</em>
<strong>implicit_taxonomies</strong> = true
<em># When no date for a page is specified, use the file creation date</em>
<strong>dates_of_creation</strong> = true</p>
<p><em># A directory where the content is loaded from</em>
<strong>content_dir</strong> = &quot;content&quot;
<em># A directory where the theme is loaded from</em>
<strong>theme_dir</strong> = &quot;themes&quot;
<em># A directory where the content is rendered to</em>
<strong>output_dir</strong> = &quot;public&quot;
<em># A subdirectory of the output directory where the assets are copied to</em>
<strong>assets</strong> = &quot;assets&quot;</p>
<p>[<strong>author</strong>]
<strong>name</strong> = &quot;&quot;
<strong>uri</strong> = &quot;&quot;
<strong>email</strong> = &quot;&quot;
<strong>avatar</strong> = &quot;&quot;</p>
<p><em># A table of tables where you can specify some data about taxonomies</em>
[<strong>taxonomies</strong>]
<em># Example with default values:</em>
<em>#tags = { name = &quot;&quot;, description = &quot;&quot;, template = &quot;taxonomy.html&quot;, key_template = &quot;taxonomy_key.html&quot;, paginate_by = ∞, sort_by_weight = false }</em>
<em># If provided, 'paginate_by' must be a positive integer</em></p>
<p><em># Any &quot;key = value&quot; of any type can be used here for templates</em>
[<strong>extra</strong>]</p>
</code>
</content>
        <updated>2020-10-04T14:14:20Z</updated>
    </entry>
    

    <entry>
        <title>Pages</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="/pages.html" />
        <id>/pages</id>
        <summary></summary>
        <content><p>Blades loads all the <a href="https://toml.io">TOML</a> files (with the <code>.toml</code> extension) from the content directory
specified in the <a href="config.html">config</a> (defaults to <code>content</code>). In these files, the page content
and metadata are provided. They are then rendered using the provided <a href="templates.html">templates</a>.</p>
<p>When the file is called <code>index.toml</code>, the corresponding page is called <strong>section</strong>. The rendered page (<code>index.html</code>) is displayed
when the user browses to the parent URL. They can use some additional data in templates,
such as their subpages and subsections. Other TOML files are treated as standard pages.</p>
<p>In pages, these variables can be specified (everything optional, default values shown):</p>
<code class="highlighted">
<p><em># Title of the page</em>
<strong>title</strong> = &quot;&quot;
<em># Date when the page was created</em>
<strong>date</strong> = None
<em># date = 2020-09-08</em></p>
<p><em># An image representing the page</em>
<strong>image</strong> = &quot;&quot;
<em># A brief summary of the page content</em>
<strong>summary</strong> = &quot;&quot;
<em># The main content of the page</em>
<em># <a href="https://commonmark.org/">CommonMark</a> markdown can be used here</em>
<strong>content</strong> = &quot;&quot;&quot;
&quot;&quot;&quot;</p>
<p><em># A template to render this page with.</em>
<em># If none is specified, the one specified in the <a href="#sections">parent section</a> is used</em>
<strong>template</strong> = &quot;&quot;
<em># A weight of the page, used if a collection this page is in is sorted by weight</em>
<strong>weight</strong> = 0
<em># A priority of this page for SEO, in the range of 0-1</em>
<strong>priority</strong> = 0.5
<em># Hide the page from the list of its parent's subpages or subsections</em>
<strong>hidden</strong> = false</p>
<p><em># A template to render the gallery pictures with</em>
<strong>gallery_template</strong> = &quot;gallery.html&quot;</p>
<p><em># A list of pictures associated with this page</em>
<em># Each will be rendered into a separate gallery page</em>
[[<strong>pictures</strong>]]
<em># Id string of the picture, used for the generated URL in the gallery page</em>
<em># MANDATORY for every picture used!</em>
<strong>pid</strong> = &quot;&quot;
<em># An associated caption of the picture</em>
<em># <a href="https://commonmark.org/">CommonMark</a> markdown can be used here</em>
<strong>caption</strong> = &quot;&quot;
<em># An alternative text displayed when the image can't be loaded of for accessibility</em>
<strong>alt</strong> = &quot;&quot;
<em># File name of the image</em>
<strong>file</strong> = &quot;&quot;
<em># Date and time of when the image was taken</em>
<strong>taken</strong> = None
<em># Repeat for every picture</em></p>
<p><em># A map of lists to classify this page with</em>
[<strong>taxonomies</strong>]
<em># For example:</em>
<em># tags = [&quot;blades&quot;, &quot;documentation&quot;]</em></p>
<p><em># Any &quot;key = value&quot; of any type can be used here for templates</em>
[<strong>extra</strong>]</p>
</code>
<h2>Sections</h2>
<p>For pages that are sections, you can additionally specify these variables:</p>
<code id="sections" class="highlighted">
<p><em># A number of pages to paginate by, if this number is exceeded</em>
<em># If provided, must be a positive integer</em>
<strong>paginate_by</strong> = ∞
<em># A template to render every subpage with (unless it specifies another template)</em>
<strong>page_template</strong> = &quot;page.html&quot;
<em># A template to render every subsection with (unless it specifies another template)</em>
<strong>section_template</strong> = &quot;section.html&quot;
<em># Sort subpages and subsetions by their provided weight, low to high</em>
<em># By default, they are sorted by their date, newer to older</em>
<strong>sort_by_weight</strong> = false</p>
</code>
<h2>Not sections</h2>
<p>For pages that are not sections, you can additionally specify these variables
(defaults are suggested):</p>
<code class="highlighted">
<p><em># The path in the output directory this page is rendered into</em>
<strong>path</strong> = {{ parent directory of the page within the content directory }}
<em># The file name this page is rendered into, without the .html extension</em>
<strong>slug</strong> = {{ file name without the extension }}</p>
</code>
</content>
        <updated>2020-10-08T09:19:32Z</updated>
    </entry>
    

    <entry>
        <title>Templates</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="/templates.html" />
        <id>/templates</id>
        <summary></summary>
        <content><p>Blades uses <a href="https://mustache.github.io/mustache.5.html">mustache</a> templates with the amazingly fast
<a href="https://github.com/maciejhirsz/ramhorns">Ramhorns</a> engine. While their syntax is extremely simple
(and can be learned in a few minutes), they are surprisingly expressive.</p>
<p>The templates are loaded from the <code>templates</code> subdirectory, or secondarily from the <code>$theme_dir/$theme/templates</code>
directory if a theme is specified in the <a href="config.html">config</a>.
Here is the list of variables at your disposal, all with their type specified.</p>
<p>These variables are common for all pages:</p>
<code class="highlighted">
<p><em>// The data of the whole site</em>
<strong>site</strong>: <a href="#site">Site</a>
<em>// Main page in the site</em>
<strong>index</strong>: <a href="#page">Page</a>
<em>// A dictionary of all the taxonomies used in the site</em>
<strong>classification</strong>: Map&lt;string, <a href="#taxonomy">Taxonomy</a>&gt;</p>
</code>
<h2>Page</h2>
<p>When rendering a page, these variables are available:</p>
<code id="page" class="highlighted">
<p><em>// Title of the page</em>
<strong>title</strong>: string
<em>// Date when the page was created</em>
<strong>date</strong>: Option&lt;<a href="#datetime">DateTime</a>&gt;
<em>// Image representing the page</em>
<strong>image</strong>: string
<em>// A brief summary of the page</em>
<strong>summary</strong>: string
<em>// The main content of the page</em>
<strong>content</strong>: string</p>
<p><em>// The full link of the page, with the site URL included</em>
<strong>permalink</strong>: string
<em>// The path of the page, beginning with <code>/</code>, without the last segment</em>
<em>// When rendered as section ({{#path}}), it acts as a list of <a href="#ancestors">Ancestors</a></em>
<strong>path</strong>: string
<em>// The trailing segment of this page's URL</em>
<em>// Without the .html extension</em>
<em>// For sections, it's the folder name rather than <code>index</code></em>
<strong>slug</strong>: string</p>
<p><em>// A list of classifications for each of the provided taxonomies</em>
<strong>taxonomies</strong>: Map&lt;string, List&lt;string&gt;&gt;
<em>// A list of pictures provided by this page</em>
<strong>pictures</strong>: List&lt;<a href="#picture">Picture</a>&gt;</p>
<p><em>// Is this page a section?</em>
<strong>is_section</strong>: bool
<em>// Is the page hidden from the list of its parent's subpages and subsections?</em>
<strong>hidden</strong>: bool
<em>// A priority of this page for SEO, in the range of 0-1</em>
<strong>priority</strong>: float</p>
<p><em>// The page one level up in the hierarchy (for the index page it's itself)</em>
<strong>parent</strong>: <a href="#page">Page</a>
<em>// The previous page on this level, if any</em>
<strong>previous</strong>: Option&lt;<a href="#page">Page</a>&gt;
<em>// The next page in this level, if any</em>
<strong>next</strong>: Option&lt;<a href="#page">Page</a>&gt;
<em>// A list of all the subpages (empty if not section)</em>
<strong>pages</strong>: List&lt;<a href="#page">Page</a>&gt;
<em>// A list of all the subsections (empty if not section)</em>
<strong>subsections</strong>: List&lt;<a href="#page">Page</a>&gt;
<em>// Available when the subpages are paginated</em>
<strong>pagination</strong>: Option&lt;<a href="#pagination">Pagination</a>&gt;</p>
<p><em>// The user provided values of any type</em>
<strong>extra</strong>: Map&lt;string, Any&gt;
<em>// Marks whether this page is the active one</em>
<em>// Can be used to highlight the current page in a list of pages</em>
<strong>active</strong>: bool</p>
</code>
<h3>Pagination</h3>
<p>When the pagination is available, you can use these variables in the pagination section
(<code>{{#pagination}} ... {{/pagination}}</code>):</p>
<code id="pagination" class="highlighted">
<p><em>// Number of the current page in the paginated pages</em>
<strong>current</strong>: integer
<em>// Number of the previous page in the paginated pages</em>
<em>// This is also its slug</em>
<strong>previous</strong>: Option&lt;integer&gt;
<em>// Number of the next page in the paginated pages</em>
<em>// This is also its slug</em>
<strong>next</strong>: Option&lt;integer&gt;
<em>// Number of the paginated pages</em>
<strong>length</strong>: integer</p>
</code>
<h3>Ancestors</h3>
<p>When the page path is used as a section (<code>{{#path}} ... {{/path}}</code>), it is interpreted
as a list of ancestors. This makes making breadcrumbs possible.
For the path segments, the following are available:</p>
<code id="ancestors" class="highlighted">
<p><em>// Name of the current path segment</em>
<strong>name</strong>: string
<em>// The full path up to this segment</em>
<strong>full</strong>: string</p>
</code>
<h3>DateTime</h3>
<p>When the date is available, you can use these variables in the datetime section
(<code>{{#date}} ... {{/date}}</code>), roughly corresponding to <a href="https://strftime.org/">strftime</a>:</p>
<code id="picture" class="highlighted">
<p><em>// Year</em>
<strong>y</strong>: integer
<em>// Month</em>
<strong>m</strong>: integer
<em>// Day, 0-padded</em>
<strong>d</strong>: integer
<em>// Day, space-padded</em>
<strong>e</strong>: integer
<em>// Hour</em>
<strong>H</strong>: integer
<em>// Minute</em>
<strong>M</strong>: integer
<em>// Second</em>
<strong>S</strong>: integer
<em>// First 3 letters of the English month name</em>
<strong>b</strong>: string
<em>// First 3 letters of the English weekday name</em>
<strong>a</strong>: string</p>
</code>
<h3>Picture</h3>
<p>When pictures are available, you can use these variables in the pictures section
(<code>{{#pictures}} ... {{/pictures}}</code> for a list of them):</p>
<code id="picture" class="highlighted">
<p><em># Id string of the picture, used for the generated URL in the gallery page</em>
<strong>pid</strong>: string
<em># An associated caption of the picture</em>
<strong>caption</strong>: string
<em># An alternative text displayed when the image can't be loaded of for accessibility</em>
<strong>alt</strong>: string
<em># File name of the image</em>
<strong>file</strong>: string
<em># Date and time of when the image was taken</em>
<strong>taken</strong>: Option&lt;<a href="#datetime">DateTime</a>&gt;
<em>// The full link of the picture, with the site URL included</em>
<strong>permalink</strong>: string</p>
</code>
<h2>Gallery</h2>
<p>When a page contains come picture, the gallery is created. The page of each photo in the gallery
gets the following variables:</p>
<code id="gallery" class="highlighted">
<p><em>// The current picture</em>
<strong>current</strong>: <a href="#picture">Picture</a>
<em>// The previous picture in the list (the last one for the first one)</em>
<strong>previous</strong>: <a href="#picture">Picture</a>
<em>// The next picture in the list (the first one for the last one)</em>
<strong>next</strong>: <a href="#picture">Picture</a>
<em>// The parent page, from which this gallery is generated</em>
<strong>parent</strong>: <a href="#page">Page</a></p>
</code>
<h2>Taxonomy</h2>
<p>Each taxonomy that is rendered gets the following variables:</p>
<code id="taxonomy" class="highlighted">
<p><em>// Full name of the taxonomy</em>
<strong>title</strong>: string
<em>// A short name of the taxonomy, used in the URL</em>
<strong>slug</strong>: string
<em>// A brief description of the taxonomy</em>
<strong>description</strong>: string
<em>// A list of keys used in this taxonomy and their corresponding pages</em>
<strong>keys</strong>: List&lt;<a href="#keypages">KeyPages</a>&gt;</p>
</code>
<h3>Key pages</h3>
<p>When keys in the taxonomy are available, you can use these variables in the keys section
(<code>{{#keys}} ... {{/keys}}</code> for a list of them):</p>
<code id="keypages" class="highlighted">
<p><em>// Name of this key (also used in the URL of the key page)</em>
<strong>key</strong>: str
<em>// All the pages with this key in this taxonomy</em>
<strong>pages</strong>: List&lt;<a href="#page">Page</a>&gt;</p>
</code>
<h2>Taxonomy key</h2>
<p>When rendering a page of a single taxonomy key, these variables are available:</p>
<code id="taxonomy-key" class="highlighted">
<p><em>// Name of this key (also used in the URL)</em>
<strong>title</strong>: string
<em>// The parent taxonomy where this key belongs to</em>
<strong>taxonomy</strong>: <a href="#taxonomy">Taxonomy</a>
<em>// The pages using this key</em>
<strong>pages</strong>: List&lt;<a href="#page">Page</a>&gt;
<em>// Optional pagination, if enabled for this taxonomy</em>
<strong>pagination</strong>: Option&lt;<a href="#pagination">Pagination</a>&gt;</p>
</code>
<h2>Site</h2>
<p>The data of the whole site, available for every page in the site section
(<code>{{#site}} ... {{/site}}</code>):</p>
<code id="site" class="highlighted">
<p><em>// The main title of the site</em>
<strong>title</strong>: string
<em>// The main URL of the site</em>
<strong>url</strong>: string
<strong>description</strong>: string
<strong>keywords</strong>: string
<em>// A representative image of the site</em>
<strong>image</strong>: string
<em>// Info about the author of the site</em>
<strong>author</strong>: <a href="#author">Author</a></p>
<p><em>// Path of the site where the assets are moved to</em>
<strong>assets</strong>: string
<em>// Is sitemap rendered?</em>
<strong>sitemap</strong>: bool
<em>// Is atom feed rendered?</em>
<strong>atom</strong>: bool
<em>// Is RSS feed rendered?</em>
<strong>rss</strong>: bool
<em>// Are taxonomies not explicitly defined in the config, but used in some page rendered?</em>
<strong>implicit_taxonomies</strong>: bool
<em>// Are pages without date provided assigned the date of file creation?</em>
<strong>dates_of_creation</strong>: bool</p>
<p><em>// The user provided values of any type</em>
<strong>extra</strong>: Map&lt;string, Any&gt;</p>
</code>
<h3>Author</h3>
<p>Info about the site author, available as a subsection of <a href="#site">site</a>
(<code>{{#site}}{{#author}} ... {{/author}}{{/site}}</code>):</p>
<code id="author" class="highlighted">
<p><strong>name</strong>: string
<strong>uri</strong>: string
<strong>email</strong>: string
<strong>avatar</strong>: string</p>
</code>
</content>
        <updated>2020-10-08T13:38:44Z</updated>
    </entry>
    

    <entry>
        <title>Themes</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="/themes/" />
        <id>/themes</id>
        <summary></summary>
        <content><p>Any site that doesn't use a theme can be used as a theme for another site.<br />
To contribute your own, submit a PR to the <a href="https://github.com/grego/blades-themes">themes repository</a>.</p>
</content>
        <updated>2020-10-12T16:54:34Z</updated>
    </entry>
    

    <entry>
        <title>casper</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="/themes/casper.html" />
        <id>/themes/casper</id>
        <summary></summary>
        <content><p>A clean blog theme, loosely based on the old Ghost.io default, but without JavaScript</p>
</content>
        <updated>2020-10-12T17:19:55Z</updated>
    </entry>
    

    <entry>
        <title>after-dark</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="/themes/after-dark.html" />
        <id>/themes/after-dark</id>
        <summary></summary>
        <content><p>Secure and accessible dark theme</p>
</content>
        <updated>2020-10-12T17:19:49Z</updated>
    </entry>
    

    <entry>
        <title>BLADE.386</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="/themes/BLADE.html" />
        <id>/themes/BLADE</id>
        <summary></summary>
        <content><p>For people who like the MS-DOS æsthetics</p>
</content>
        <updated>2020-10-12T17:11:39Z</updated>
    </entry>
    

</feed>